（審判）これより
決勝トーナメント決勝戦—
The playoff game between Teiko
and Kamata West will now begin.
帝光(ていこう)中学校 対 鎌田西(かまたにし)中学校の
試合を始めます
一同 礼！
Bow!
（選手一同）
よろしくお願いします！
Let's have a good game!
（赤司(あかし)）これで最後だ
勝てば優勝… そして２連覇となる
This is the last game.
If we win, we're champions
for the second year in a row.
Do you have anything to say?
（赤司）何か言うことはあるか？
（緑間(みどりま)）１本でも多くスリーを
決める それだけなのだよ
I'll make as many threes as I can.
That's all.
（青峰(あおみね)）別に なんもねーよ
Nothing, really.
（紫原(むらさきばら)）んー… 早く終わらせて
お菓子食べたい
Let's finish this quickly
so I can have more snacks.
（黄瀬(きせ)）なんか みんな
バラバラじゃないっスか!?
You guys are all over the place!
フッ… かまわないさ
It doesn't matter.
バラバラの個性が
かみ合ってこそのチームだ
Our team brings those scattered
personalities together.
共有すべきことは ただ１つ
We only need one thing in common.
（赤司）勝つぞ！
（一同）オオ！
Let's win!
Yeah!
（白金(しろがね)）
青峰には 何もしなくていい
Don't do anything for Aomine.
Huh?
（白金）
今までどおりにしていればいい
Keep doing what you're doing.
励ましや慰めは逆効果だ
Encouragement and consolation
would be counterproductive.
If he needs it, I'll do it.
必要ならば私が話そう
（青峰）だあっ… でいっ！
（鎌田西選手）うあっ！
We Are No Longer
Teiko
Kamata West
Aomine.
（白金）青峰
（青峰）あ…
（白金）少しここに残れ
Hang back a bit.
ゴホッ… ゴホッ…
私はオマエに謝らねばならん
I need to apologize to you.
（白金）オマエがとてつもない
才能を秘めていることには—
I realized immediately you
possessed incredible talent.
すぐに気付いた
誰よりバスケットを
好きであることにも…
That you loved basketball
more than your peers, too.
そして その才能が開花すれば
今のようになるであろうことにも
I knew this would happen
if your talents blossomed.
I knew, but I said nothing.
気付いていながら
何も言わなかった…
I couldn't say anything.
言えなかったのだ
My desire to see your
オマエの気持ちより—
その才能が開いた先が見たい
という感情が まさってしまった
talents blossom was greater than
my consideration for your feelings.
I'm sorry, but please.
だから謝る そして頼む
その才能をムダにしないでほしい
Don't waste that talent.
What?
（白金）オマエの悩みは
すぐに解決できることではない
Your problem can't be resolved immediately.
だがいつか解決できるかもしれん
But it may be eventually.
Don't give up.
投げ出すな
あきらめなければ必ずとは言わん
I can't guarantee anything, but you'll
have nothing left if you give up.
だが あきらめたら何も残らん
（青峰）ちょっ… 今のセリフ！
（白金）うむ パクった
Hey, that's...
Yes, I stole it.
You were listening?
聞いてたってこと!?
ハア… 分かったっス
I get it.
There's no turning back now, but...
今さらもう元には戻れねえ
それでも…
I still want to win.
まだ勝ちたいって気持ちは残ってる
（赤司）フッ！
（黒子(くろこ)）えいっ！
（紫原）フンッ！
（青峰）えいっ！
Teiko
Kamata West
やったっスー！ ウハハッ
We did it!
ハア…
（紫原）これでもう
お菓子食ってもいいっしょ〜
Now I can eat, right?
てか食うー？
Want some?
（緑間）ああ もらおう
（紫原）え!? マジで!?
Yes, please.
What? Seriously?
Why are you just standing there?
（虹村(にじむら)）何ぼーっとしてんだよ
もっと喜んでいいんだぞ
You can celebrate more.
（黄瀬）黒子っちのパスが
ドンピシャで決まって…
Go.
（虹村）行けよ せめて今だけでも
素直になっていいじゃねーか
You can at least be honest
about your feelings now.
（真田(さなだ)）
一段落… という感じですね
That's that, I guess.
（白金）ああ… そうだな
Yes.
（真田）虹村たちは
引退してしまいましたが—
The third-years quit,
but there's nothing to worry about.
きっと心配ないでしょう
（真田）“キセキの世代”と
呼ばれる彼らがいれば…
We still have the Generation of Miracles.
I wouldn't be so sure.
（白金）どうかな？
（真田）は？
What?
逆に私は心配だ
彼らの力は大きすぎる
I'm actually worried.
They're too strong.
チームをまとめるには むしろ—
We'll have to help them
keep the team together.
これから私たちが
フォローしていかねば…
ゴホッ… ウッ…
それは大丈夫でしょう
あなたがいれば きっと…
They'll be fine.
As long as you're around, I'm sure—
He'll live.
（真田）命に別状はない
だが… 残念ながら
監督に復帰することは もうない
But unfortunately, he can't coach anymore.
（一同）な…
（真田）よって今日から—
So as of today, I am your head coach.
私が監督を引き継ぐことになった
明日からは今までどおりの
練習メニューに入る いいな
We'll practice as normal starting tomorrow.
Got it?
（紫原）ぬうぅぅ！
（部員たち）ううっ… うわぁあ！
決めたからいいが
今のはオマエに２人ついていた
You made the shot,
but there were two guys on you.
オレに戻したほうが
より確実だったはずだぞ
You should have passed the ball to me.
あー… そう？ まーいーじゃん
決めたんだし
Really?
Who cares? I made the shot.
（さつき）ムッ君…
別人のように強くなってる…
Mukkun's becoming stronger, like Aomine-kun.
まるで青峰君みたいに…
But that's why I fear his sudden growth.
けど だからこそ…
この急成長が 私には怖い
（黄瀬）紫原っち さっきの
シュートすごくないっスか？
Murasakibaracchi, that was an amazing shot!
（紫原）ん？ んー… そう？
けどなんか…
Really? But...
力がわいて
しょーがないんだよね〜
I just feel so powerful.
本気出したら つい味方でも
ひねり潰しちゃうかもしんない
If I actually tried, I could
probably crush my teammates.
If I can make it from here...
（緑間）もし… この距離から…
ハア…
（理事長）“キセキの世代”と
呼ばれている５人の生徒—
You must play the five students known as
彼らを今後何があっても
必ず試合に出しなさい
the Generation of Miracles in
every game, no matter what.
Chairman's Office
なっ… しかし！
What? But—
（理事長）ヒーローの活躍は
大いに宣伝になる
Those heroes will do much
to publicize our school.
しかも彼らは入部以来
負けなしだそうじゃないか
I heard they haven't lost
since they joined the team.
（真田）
ですが 彼らはまだ子供です！
But they're still children!
特別扱いをしては
よくないときも…
We shouldn't give them special treatment!
（理事長）その特別扱いを
しろと言ってるんだ
I'm telling you to give
them special treatment.
（黒子）今日の紫原君は
すごかったですね
Murasakibara-kun was amazing today.
（さつき）うん… そうだね
Yeah, he was.
けど… 同時に怖くもなりました
But I'm afraid of his growth, too.
彼の成長ぶりを見ていると…—
青峰君が変わってしまったときの
ことを思い出します
It reminds me of how Aomine-kun changed.
Have you talked to him recently?
テツ君は最近 青峰君と話した？
全中が終わってからは まだ…
Not since nationals.
何とかしたいとは
思っているのですが—
I want to do something,
but I don't know what.
正直 今のボクには分かりません
桃井(ももい)さん？
Momoi-san?
みんな…—
You'll
ずっと一緒だよね？
always be together, right?
これからもずっと仲良く
一緒にやっていけるよね!?
You'll be friends forever, right?
はい ずっと—
Yes. We'll always be
一緒です
together.
Seijuro,
部活動の全国大会で
優勝したそうだな
I heard you won the national tournament.
Yes.
（赤司）はい
（赤司の父）学業のほうはどうだ
（赤司）問題ありません
What about school?
It's going smoothly.
（赤司の父）フン… ならばいい
Fine, then.
両方この調子で続けなさい
Keep doing what you're doing.
文武両道… あらゆる面で
秀でてこそ赤司家の人間だ
A member of the Akashi family
must excel in all domains.
（赤司）はい 父さん
Yes, Father.
（青峰）ざけんなよ！
Don't be ridiculous!
毎回毎回あっさり
抜かれてんじゃねーよ！
Quit letting me past you!
止められなくても何かしねーと—
Even if you can't stop me, if you do
nothing, you're not helping at all!
ヘルプもへったくれも
ねーだろーが！
（部員）やってるよ…
I'm trying.
青峰君がすごすぎるんだって！
You're just too good.
None of us can stop you...
君を止められるヤツなんて
いっこないよ…
くそがっ！ やってられっか！
Damn it!
I don't have time for this!
（さつき）青峰君！
（真田）待て 青峰！
Aomine-kun!
Wait, Aomine!
（真田）青峰
Aomine...
（青峰）あ… コー… 監督
Head Coach...
（真田）監督として
青峰のしたことは—
As his coach, I can't overlook what he did.
不問にするわけにはいかない…
だが今の青峰に練習を強要し
部を辞めるとでも言いだしたら…
But if forcing him to practice
will make him quit the team...
If you don't want to,
オマエが嫌ならば…
練習にはもう来なくてもいい
you don't have to come to practice anymore.
ただし 試合には出るんだ
But you must come to games.
出て勝てば 文句は言わん
If you play and win, we won't have a problem.
Aomine-kun,
（黒子）青峰君
let's go back to practice.
練習に戻りましょう
Why?
（青峰）なんでだよ
何のために練習すんだよ？
Why practice?
（青峰）試合に出れば
嫌でも勝っちまうのに？
Even though I'm guaranteed
to win any game I play?
戦意も失せた相手を—
Do I need to crush my disheartened
opponents even harder?
これまで以上にたたき潰せるように
なりゃいいのか？
（黒子）
気持ちは分かります けど…
I understand how you feel, but...
（青峰）分かる？
You understand?
はっ 何が分かるんだよ！
教えてくれよ！
What is it you understand? Tell me.
オメエみてーに１人じゃ
なんにもできないようなヤツに—
What could someone so powerless understand?
何が分かんだよ！
ボクだって…
Even I'm
青峰君やみんなを
うらやましいと思うときはある
jealous of you and the others sometimes.
けどできないことを嘆いても
仕方がない！
But crying about it won't do any good!
だからボクは
全力でパスを回すために…
That's why I do my best to pass—
（青峰）
誰に回すんだよ そのパスは
Who do you pass to?
Even without your passes,
I could beat anyone myself.
（青峰）
オマエのパスがなくても もう—
オレは１人でどんなヤツにも
勝てちまうのに？
The only one who can beat me
（青峰）オレに勝てるのは—
is me.
オレだけだ
You haven't passed to me once since then.
（青峰）あんときから
オマエのパスはもらってねえ…
ついこの間なのに
もうずいぶん昔のことみてーだ
It happened so recently,
but it seems so long ago.
オレは…—
I don't
もうオマエのパスを
どうやって取ればいいのかも—
even know how to receive your passes anymore.
忘れちまった
（黄瀬）
ぶっちゃけどうなんスかねー
I'm not sure Aominecchi
should be playing games whether
he comes to practice or not.
練習に来ようが来まいが
青峰っちは試合に出すって
I don't know what the coach is
thinking, but I'm hesitant to agree.
監督の真意は分からないが
正直賛成しかねるな
About that...
（紫原）そのことなんだけどさ〜
If we don't have to practice
as long as we win,
練習しなくても
勝てばいいっていうんなら—
オレだってしたくないんだよね〜
I don't want to practice anymore.
Don't be stupid.
バカを言うな
そんなこと許せるはずがない
He'll never allow it.
But I can't lose.
（紫原）だってー
負ける気がしないんだもん オレー
それに今まで赤ちんの言うことだけ
聞いてたのはさぁ〜
Besides, I've only been listening to you
because I thought I couldn't beat you.
赤ちんには絶対勝てないと
思ってたからなんだよねー
けど最近 だんだんそーでもない
かもって思ってきたんだー
But lately, I think that might
not be the case anymore.
オレより弱い人の言うこと
聞くのは… やだなぁ
I don't want to listen to
someone weaker than me.
なんだと？
What did you say?
急に何言ってるの？
ムッ君 冗談でしょ!?
What are you talking about?
You're joking, right?
（赤司）どけ
（さつき）う… あ…
Move.
力ずくでなければならないのなら
そうするまでだ
If I have to do it by force, I will.
うぬぼれるなよ
Don't flatter yourself.
ワンオンワン ５本先取だ
One-on-one.
First to five.
（真田）なんてことを
言ってしまったんだ！
What have I done?
Why couldn't I have trusted Aomine?
なぜあのとき 青峰のことを
信じてやれなかった!?
なぜ！
Why?
（緑間）なっ…
（さつき）そんな…
What?
No way...
Akashi               Murasakibara
（黄瀬）まさかここまで
一方的になるなんて…
I didn't think it'd be this one-sided...
（紫原）正直ちょっとというか…
かなりガッカリかも〜
（赤司）ハア… ハア…
Honestly, I'm pretty disappointed.
I can't listen to you anymore.
やっぱこの程度の人の
言うこと聞くのは 無理かなー
（赤司）
ハア… ハア… クッ…
（紫原）
まーいっか これ決めたら—
Whatever.
Once I make this, I'm doing what I want.
約束どおり これからは
オレの好きなようにするから〜
I, Akashi Seijuro, lost?
（赤司）オレが…
赤司征十郎が負ける？
That's impossible.
ありえない… そんなこと…
あってはならない！
It cannot be.
勝たなければならない…
I must win, no matter my opponent.
誰が相手でも… 何があっても…
No matter what.
Winning is everything.
この世は勝利がすべてだ
勝者は肯定され 敗者は否定される
Winners are validated and losers are denied.
（赤司）
すべてに勝つ僕は すべて正しい
Because I always win, I am always right.
（黄瀬）
ちょっ… 今何が起きたんスか!?
What just happened?
分からないのだよ…
I don't know.
（さつき）何か違う…
今までの赤司君じゃない…
Something's different.
Akashi-kun's not his normal self.
（赤司）
少し調子に乗りすぎだぞ 敦(あつし)
You're pushing your luck, Atsushi.
あまり僕を怒らせるな
Don't make me so angry.
I never forgive those who defy me.
僕に逆らうヤツは—
親でも許さない
Not even my parents.
Akashi                          Murasakibara
5                             4
じゃーオレあがんね〜 お疲れ〜
Well, I'm out.
Good work, guys.
（さつき）ちょっ… ムッ君！
（紫原）だから〜
Wait, Mukkun!
I just have to come to
practice tomorrow, right?
明日からもちゃんと来れば
いいんでしょ 練習〜
（赤司）いや… その話はもういい
No, that's fine.
好きにするといい
試合に勝ちさえすればな
You can do as you please as long as we win.
What?
（緑間）何を言っているのだよ
赤司！ それではさっきと…
What are you saying, Akashi?
That's not what—
The same goes for you two, as well.
（赤司）
緑間 黄瀬についても同様だ
試合で勝てば
それ以外は不問にする
As long as we win,
I don't care what you do.
At our level, forcing everyone
to cooperate is pointless.
（赤司）僕たちのレベルでは—
無理に足並みを
そろえようとするほうがムダだ
むしろ合わせないほうが
効率がいい
It's more effective if we don't.
（部員）そんな…
But...
それじゃもうチームプレーを
するなって言ってるようにしか…
It sounds like you're telling
us not to use teamwork.
That's exactly right.
そのとおりだ
Teamwork will only get in the way
of the Generation of Miracles.
“キセキの世代”にとって—
チームプレーは
邪魔なものでしかない
そう言ったんだ
That's what I said.
You're late.
（赤司）遅かったな…
Looks like you failed.
どうやらダメだったようだね
Yes.
はい…
ならばもう仕方ないな
青峰のことはあきらめろ
Then it can't be helped.
Give up on Aomine.
（赤司）一度ヒビの入った皿は
元に戻ることはない
Once a plate cracks, it
will never be whole again.
But as long as it's still useful,
things are fine as they are.
だが使えるなら 今のままで充分だ
赤司… 君？
Akashi-kun?
What was up with Akashicchi?
（黄瀬）さっきの赤司っち
なんだったんスかね？
He was like a different person.
まるで別人っていうか…
A different person...
（緑間）別人…
まさにそのとおりだ
He's exactly right.
あの雰囲気は 今まで何度か
見てきた あいつそのものだ
That demeanor, which I've seen
many times before, is him.
What are you talking about?
（黒子）何を言ってるんですか？
いえ…—
No,
who are you?
君は誰ですか？
I'm Akashi Seijuro, of course.
（赤司）僕は赤司征十郎に
決まっているだろう
テツヤ
Tetsuya.
（緑間）赤司の中にはもう１人
別の赤司がいる
There's another, different Akashi inside him.
I can hardly believe it myself.
自分でも信じられない話だが—
しかし…
But...
I heard you told the others they
don't have to come to practice.
（真田）私のいない間に紫原たちに
来なくていいと言ったそうだな…
（赤司）帝光の理念は勝つこと
Teiko's doctrine is victory.
僕は監督の判断は正しいと思います
You made the right decision.
Prioritizing victory and
abandoning teamwork...
（真田）勝つことを最優先した
チームプレーの排除…
そしてそれは 事実強い…
It is truly strong.
だが 果たしてこれが
チームと呼べるのか？
But can you really call this a team?
Murasakibara isn't coming today?
（緑間）紫原は今日も休みか？
Neither is Aomine-san.
（部員）それと 青峰さんも…
（黄瀬）やっぱ変わったっスよねー
Things have changed.
What has?
（緑間）何がなのだよ
（黄瀬）
なんか殺伐としてるっつーか…
It seems so inhuman now.
減ったっスよね
仲間意識みたいな そういう感覚
We've lost our sense of companionship.
It's been like this since the coach
and Akashicchi changed their policy.
監督と赤司っちが
方針変えてからっスよね
緑間っちも
イラついてるじゃないっスか
You seem irritated, too.
（緑間）どんな形だろうと
部の方針なら それに従うまで
I will follow the team's policy,
no matter what it is.
I just don't like how Aomine
and Murasakibara are acting.
オレが気にくわんのは
今の青峰と紫原だ
理由はどうあれ—
Whatever the reason,
練習に来なくていいと言われて
来ないような神経は—
I can't understand why someone
wouldn't come to practice.
理解に苦しむのだよ
人事を尽くさんヤツらとなど
仲良くはできんな
I can't be friends with someone who
doesn't do everything humanly possible.
You don't usually practice shooting.
（赤司）
珍しいな シュートの練習など
（黒子）赤司君…
Akashi-kun...
You don't need to do that anymore.
（赤司）もうオマエには
必要のない練習だろう？
ん… そうですね
You're right.
赤司君はバスケは好きですか？
Do you like basketball?
（赤司）質問の意味が分からないな
I don't understand your question.
その“好き”という感情は
勝つために必要か？
Do I need to like it to win?
（黒子）ボクは…
分からなくなってきました
I'm not sure anymore.
今のバスケ部は
明らかに変わりました
The team has clearly changed
ever since you changed.
赤司君が変わってしまった
あのときから…
This again?
またその話か
僕は変わってなどいない
I haven't changed.
元から僕は２人いて…
それが入れ替わっただけだ
I always had two personalities.
The other simply took over.
I'm not hiding anything.
（赤司）別に隠すつもりなどない
信じようが信じまいが
テツヤの自由だ
Whether or not you believe me is up to you.
ただもし そのことを
変わったというのならば—
But if you call that change,
then I say it was necessary.
それは必要だったからだ
僕が変わったから
チームが変わったのではない
The team didn't change because I changed.
I changed because the team changed.
チームが変わったから
僕も変わったんだ
Now that our talents are awakening,
we have no rivals outside anymore.
みんなの突出した才能が
目覚めはじめ—
もはや外に敵はいなくなった
If there are any, they're within the team.
あるとすれば内側だ
大きすぎる力を
無理にまとめようとすれば—
Forcing us to work together
could make the team implode.
内部から崩壊する可能性がある
僕らはもう 力を合わせる
べきではないんだよ
We shouldn't work together anymore.
What are you...
そんな… 何を言って…
That's why you and Daiki had a falling out.
（赤司）
だがオマエと大輝(だいき)はそうなった
光と影とも呼べる
オマエたち２人でも—
The light became too bright for his shadow.
光だけが強すぎたことで
合わなくなっていった
それが光と光ならば
火を見るより明らかだ
If you were comparing two
lights, it would be obvious.
勝つこと以上に大事なことは…
ないんですか？
Isn't anything more important than winning?
No.
ない
（赤司）
漠然とした理想など無力なだけだ
Vague ideals are powerless.
そのとおり… なの…
かもしれないですね
You might
be right.
成長すれば人は変わっていく…
People change as they grow.
Maybe I was just desperate
for things to be like
なのにボクは
全中に優勝する前—
あの頃にただ…—
必死で戻りたかった
だけなのかもしれません
they were before nationals.
もし辞めたいのならば止めはしない
If you want to quit, I won't stop you.
だが 続けたいのならば受け入れろ
But if you're staying, you must accept it
この先も… 帝光のシックスマンで
あり続けたいのなら
if you want to keep being Teiko's sixth man.
Preview
Hello, Kuroko?
（荻原）もしもし 黒子？
It's been a while, Ogiwara-kun.
（黒子）久しぶりですね 荻原君
（荻原）なんかあったのか？
Did something happen?
No, I'm fine.
（黒子）いえ… 大丈夫です
（荻原）ならいいけど…—
That's fine, then.
If you ever want to talk, call me.
What is Victory?
話したいことあったら
いつでも電話してこいよ
Okay.
（黒子）はい…